Paul Barfield

7237 Blackwillow Lane Dallas, Texas 75249 paulbarfield2@gmail.com (817) 217-4192

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY:

QA / Food Safety Manager with 20+ years' experience. HACCP Certified / SQF Practitioner - Implemented SQF and Maintained BRC. Skilled in managing Laboratories, Employee Conflict, and Change. Worked in protein arena with: Pork Slaughter / Further Processing. Beef Slaughter / Further Processing. Poultry Further Processing. Worked with Dairy, Salted Snacks, Sauces, Fats and Oils, Hot and Cold Filled Beverages.

EDUCATION:

ASHFORD UNIVERSITY | SAN DIEGO, CA BACHELOR OF ARTS / ORGANIZATIONAL MANAGEMENT (GPA 3.54) May, 2017

SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS:

- HACCP Certified, Pennsylvania State University
- USDA and FDA Label Approval
- Continuous Improvement
- FSIS 9 CFR Knowledge
- Statistical Process Control Experience
- Organic Certification Experience
- Microsoft Office Suite, / Apple OS-X

- SQF Practitioner 2000 Code
- Master Sanitation Plan
- Chemistry / Microbiology
- FDA 21 CFR Knowledge
- Six Sigma / Lean Manufacturing
- Kosher (Star-K) Experience
- SAP Experience

SUMMARY OF EXPERIENCE:

- Managing All Aspects of Quality and Food Safety
- Beef Grinding and Processing
- Managing Department Budget
- 3rd Party / In House Sanitation
- Implementing GFSI Certification Audit
- Monthly Internal Audit
- Animal Welfare, Handling, and Transportation
- Liaison to USDA
- Document Control
- Resolving Customer Complaints
- New Product Label Approval

- Managing a Staff of up to 38 Employees
- Pork Processing
- Managing Onsite Laboratory
- 3rd Party Pest Control
- Comprehensive Employee Training
- Pathogen Elimination
- HACCP Program / Plan
- SSOP Program
- Change Management
- Conflict Resolution
- Child Nutrition Labeling

WORK HISTORY

HACCP PLAN TASK CONSULTANT

PROMETRIC

BALTIMORE, MD

MAY, 2017 - PRESENT

Company specializes in creating training for building HACCP Plans.

ACCOMPLISHMENTS: Contributing to development of HACCP Training program to assist people in learning how to create new HACCP and HARP-C Plans, GFSI Audit Testing.

QUALITY ASSURANCE MANAGER

NOAH'S ARK PROCESSORS DAWSON, MN

MAY, 2016 – JANUARY, 2017

Plant Manufactures Kosher, Frozen, Ground Beef, Raw and RTE Beef Deli Products.

ACCOMPLISHMENTS: Guided the plant through an FSA with no NR's and no Action. Developed

Expertise at Pathogen Elimination.

Leadership: Rewrote the Listeria Control program. Increased the plants food safety awareness 35% through monthly food safety topic training.

Reason for Leaving: Company downsized and eliminated my position

DIRECTOR OF TECHNICAL SERVICES

DEVAULT FOODS

MALVERN, PA MARCH – DECEMBER, 2014

Plant Manufactures Frozen, Raw and RTE Beef & Poultry Patties, Meatballs and Philly Steaks. ACCOMPLISHMENTS: Guided the plant through two FSA's and one BRC Audit (Score A) Reason for Leaving: Company Downsized, eliminating Director role.

FOOD SAFETY SUPERINTENDENT

JBS USA.

SOUDERTON, PA.

AUGUST, 2012 - DECEMBER, 2013

Plant is a Beef Slaughter Establishment That Processes 2000 Head Per Day.

ACCOMPLISHMENTS: Closed out a 2011 N.O.I.E. and achieved Robust Animal Handling status.

Answered 46 (previously unanswered) NR's in two months. Reduced the number of NR's in forthcoming year by 50% through Technical Training. Increased BRC Audit score from B to an A during the transition between my first and second years.

Leadership: Developed a cross training schedule to assist all technicians on how to perform every job on the Harvest Floor. Increased Supervisor skills by teaching how to use the ladder of inference to get to the center of conflict between team members. Laboratory: We learned how to select which lots of product trim to retain on Hold by evaluating the E. coli 0157:H7 samples and determining which positives and close positives to keep and send to cooker.

Reason for Leaving: Company Re-Organization, eliminated QA management team.

QUALITY ASSURANCE MANAGER

PELLEGRINO FOODS

WARREN. PA.

AUGUST, 2010 – AUGUST, 2012

Plant is a Co-Packer that Manufactures Fully Cooked, Frozen USDA and FDA Products.

ACCOMPLISHMENTS: Increased efficiency of Pre-Operational Inspection, Re-wrote two HACCP Plans, Developed two others. Developed Comprehensive Master Sanitation Plan. First person in US to gain USDA Label Approval for Bacon Brownies, Obtained SQF Level 2 status 2nd year.

Leadership: Led plant through first SQF Certification by implementing SQF Non-Compliances during monthly Internal Audit. Taught management how to comply using SQF Manual. Taught team how to work together to determine corrective actions for pre-operational inspections and SSOP Deviations.

Laboratory: Purchased a 3M Petri Film plate reader for E-Coli and APC swabs, then Neogen ATP swabs for pre-op sanitation samples. Reason for Leaving: Took promotional opportunity.

HACCP COORDINATOR

SMITHFIELD PACKING COMPANY

SMITHFIELD, VA. OCTOBER, 2004 – JULY, 2010

Plant is a Pork Slaughter Manufacturer That Processes 14,000 Head Per Day.

ACCOMPLISHEMENTS: Learned how to write HACCP Plans; How to monitor for HACCP, SSOP, & GMP Effectiveness, USDA Laison; Learned several different training methods. Developed Document Control skills. Reason for Leaving: Offered a QA Manager position.

PREVIOUS EXERIENCES.

DALLAS, TEXAS

OCTOBER 1990 - AUGUST - 2004

ACCOMPLISHMENTS; Learned how to complete Chemistry Titrations, HPLC, Microbiology Plating and Counting and various other analytical assays. In-Line QA Technician monitoring duties.